Hey everybody, this is the content video
going over section 1.2 of your textbook.
This is the hardware
and software section.
So this is going to be maybe somewhat
basic for some of you, but that's
okay. We're just going to quickly
review it and go over some different
components about computers. And you
might think, why is this important
in the context of programming?
Well, it's important to know how the
code that you write interacts with the
different components of a computer.
It's not just magic commands that
you write that make it do stuff.
There's pretty good
systems to all of it. So to
start off with, we're going
to just talk about some
of the differences between
hardware and software.
We'll briefly touch on
Moore's Law, computer
organization, input-output units, memory,
the CPU, and then software.
So very first, hardware and software.
So hardware, that's kind of the
basic concept is that's the physical
components of a computer that
make it run. And these are the
things that you can touch. you can
dismantle, you can take them apart,
you can rebuild them. They're going to
be things like your CPU, your
memory, your RAM, fans, thermal sync,
motherboard, anything else that is
a component, a physical component
of your computer that comes together
to create the actual computer.
We'll talk about the CPU in a little
more depth in just a few moments,
but like I said, we touched on RAM
for a minute, so that stands for
Random Access Memory, or just memory
is what a lot of people will call
it, that enables you to store data
for currently open applications.
So for example, right now I'm
running Zoom, an internet browser.
Typically you have an Outlook
tab open as well, and RAM
helps all of those applications
to run simultaneously.
You probably also have a bunch of
applications open. Again, that's
going to be your RAM keeping those
things running and running smoothly.
Another key component to
hardware is going to be your
motherboard, which handles
a lot of the input and
output data that's coming
into your computer or laptop.
And I think, yeah, that's kind of
a basic introduction to hardware.
We'll get to software in a second,
but let's talk a little bit more
about some of these components.
But I also, before we move too far
into that, want to talk about
Moore's Law. So this is section 1.2.1
of your textbook. And Moore's Law is
a fairly simple concept. Basically
what it says is that technology
is constantly improving and what
you might expect current computers
and current trends to have now
is um well I guess let me let me
rephrase that uh in about 18 months
if you were to go to your favorite
computer store Apple, Dell, HP,
Best Buy I don't know wherever
you guys go to get your technology
high um you go to that store and you
walk in and what you would expect
to see 18 months from now is that
a lot of the machines in there,
most all of them have doubled in
their capacity since today. So today,
uh, 2026, let's say we go to the
store in, uh, 2027 or 2028. Um,
and you, you see the computers have
doubled, tripled in their capacity.
Um, they're faster, they're more
robust, they can handle more
data. That idea is Moore's law.
It's, um, it's just something that I
want you to kind of keep in mind in
the back of your head as you take
this course that the things that
we code and the things that we
create in this class they're going
to be awesome and they're going to
be great for now but thinking
forward what things are going to be
created that are going to be faster
and stronger and easier than the
things that we'll create in this
course now and how can you keep up with
your own skills to stay on top
of those changing times so for
example generative AI can code basically
everything that you're going to
learn in this class so what does
that mean to you as a student who's
learning how to code why do these
things matter to you and what
does it mean right now learning to
code when AI can just do it for you
why is it still important that you
are code literate so to speak so
just keeping keep those things in
the back of your head okay let's
move on to computer organization
so we've got kind of two different
logical units or sections, like
it says here, we've got input
units and output units or input
devices and output devices.
So input devices, this is pretty
straightforward. It's anything that
gives data or units for processing
into the computer. So for example,
right now I am recording a video.
I'm also scrolling with my mouse.
My computer is picking
up audio that is coming
in and it's going to
transcribe all of that.
So these are all input
devices. And here's
another couple of examples, thumb drives,
GPS,
ebooks, memory sticks, the Nintendo
Switch. Actually, just kidding,
that's an example under
something else. But a device that
responds to up, down, left, right,
forward, backward, accelerations.
So those are all types
of input devices that you
might see on a computer
or a type of computer.
And on the flip side,
we've got output devices.
Those are going to be
things that are giving data
back out. So it's not
taking data in, it's giving
data out. These are
things like your screen.
That's all I can think of off
the top of my head. Audio,
video, I'm just going to
read from the textbook here.
I often think of printers for some
reason. I guess it's just because
like in my head, the paper comes
out and so that's an output device.
But yeah, there's other forms, virtual
reality devices, PlayStation, VR,
you know, pick your favorite,
right? There's a lot of
different output devices. So
pretty simple concepts there.
Let's move down to memory
units. So we talked about
RAM a minute ago. RAM stands
for random access memory.
Most computers as a standard
contain 8 to 16 gigabytes of RAM.
You probably have somewhere in
that range unless you've got
a super cool computer and you've
customized it. That's great.
And that's kind of it here. I
guess it's worth mentioning that
gigabytes stands for, or GB stands
for gigabytes. A gigabyte is
a billion bytes and a byte is
eight bits. A bit is either a zero
or a one. So there's kind of a
hierarchy, not hierarchy, but
kind of a chain there of how these
data points are all connected.
Quite a bit of data here,
a billion bytes. So very
cool. Okay, let's skip over
arithmetic and logic unit
and jump down to central
processing unit or CPU.
I like to think of the CPU as
the brain of your computer.
It does all of the thinking,
all the processing.
Well, I guess not all of it,
but it takes the inputs and the
outputs or it processes the
inputs and outputs sorry it can do
quite a bit all at once and you
can read all about that here
a lot of them have multi-core
or sorry well yeah multi-core
processors dual core processors
we've got quad core processors
octa core processors these are
things that can like it says
here execute billions of instructions
per second and that's why
technology is so fast and it's
able to run so many things all at
once and again you you think about
the brain you think about how
you want your brain to be making
snap decisions and and the same
goes for your computer you want
it to be running quickly smoothly
and able to take a lot of data
all at once and do a lot with that
okay um and I think we're probably
going to wrap up about there
So since this is the hardware
and software section,
I do briefly want to just
talk about software. So
software is what drives
the hardware of a computer.
It's written by men or men or women as a
set of instructions fed to the computer.
I often think of softwares
as like, I don't know, like
Microsoft Word or Tableau
or something that's kind
of like a package that you
download and install. all.
And that's true that those are
very detailed sets of instructions
that have been programmed and
set up as software that you can
download onto your computer. But
a lot of softwares are just basic
things like your operating system.
So if you're running Windows,
Mac operating system, Linux, any others
out there, those are very detailed
instructions as well that are
telling your computer how to run and
how to do basic things such as here's
how you pop up a window and here's
how you have a background and
here's you know everything else that
um it has to do with what your computer
is actually doing with the hardware
components so hardware the things
that you can touch i don't know
why i thought of smell but you can
also smell them um and the software
are the things that you do on the
computer with the hardware so i mean
like if minecraft is your favorite
software that's amazing um so that
about wraps up this video on hardware
and software Thanks for watching.